<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="cv2html.xsl"?>

<resume keywords="Metareasoning, Artificial Intelligence, Search, Digital Typography">

  <person>
    <firstname>David</firstname>
    <lastname>Tolpin</lastname>
    <contactinfo>
	  <email>dvd@offtopia.net</email>
      <www>http://offtopia.net/</www>
      <phone>+972-58-40-320-60, +44-7435-869-734</phone>
	  <address>
        <street>PO Box 5164</street>
        <city>Be'er Sheva</city>
            <zip>84151</zip>
        <country>Israel</country>
      </address>
    </contactinfo>
  </person>

  <objective>
      <para>
          Applied researcher &#x2014; a position in a research team where I 
          conduct theoretical research and apply it to practical innovations.
		  Available for hire in Israel with 2 month's notice.
      </para>
  </objective>

  <interests>
      <para>
        Artificial Intelligence, probabilistic reasoning, bayesian statistics,
        decision-making under uncertainty, problem-solving search.
    </para>
  </interests>

  <education>
    <diploma since="2009" till="2013">
      <school>Ben-Gurion University of the Negev</school>
      <degree>Ph.D. Thesis: "Rational Metareasoning in Problem-Solving Search"</degree>
	  <award when="2012">Friedman research excellence award.</award>
    </diploma>
    <diploma since="2007" till="2009">
      <school>Ben Gurion University of the Negev</school>
      <degree>M.Sc. in Computer Science. Thesis: "Limited Rationality Approach to Optimization under Uncertainty".</degree>
    </diploma>

    <diploma>
      <school>Moscow State Technical University</school>
      <degree>M.Sc. in Applied Mechanics. Thesis: "A Model for Chaotic Behavior in Deep Drilling".</degree>
    </diploma>
   </education>


  <employments>
	<employment since="2014" till="current">
	  <company url="http://www.ox.ac.uk/">University of Oxford</company>
	  <position>Post-Doctoral Researcher</position>
	  <experience>
		  <itemizedlist>
			  <listitem>Probabilistic Programming &#x2014; developed <ulink url="https://bitbucket.org/dtolpin/anglican">Anglican</ulink>, a probabilistic programming system capable of solving real-world inference problems.</listitem>
			  <listitem>Approximate Inference &#x2014; introduced and implemented a new adaptive Metropolis-Hastings algorithm for probabilistic programming, publication under review.</listitem>
			  <listitem>Bayesian Statistics &#x2014; <ulink url="http://arxiv.org/abs/1502.07314">applications</ulink> of probabilistic programming to reinforcement learning.</listitem>
		  </itemizedlist>
      </experience>
	</employment>

    <employment since="2007" till="2014">
      <company url="http://www.bgu.ac.il/">Ben Gurion University of the Negev</company>
      <position>Lecturer</position>
      <experience>
          <para>Principles of programming languages, system programming, computer architecture, compiler construction (TA).</para>
        <award when="2013">Excellence in teaching award.</award>
      </experience>
    </employment>

    <employment since="January, 2005" till="February, 2006">
		<company url="http://today.yougov.com/">Polimetrix/YouGov</company>
      <position>Consultant</position>
	  <experience>Joined the startup at an early stage. Designed and developed
		  the online survey system used by the company, along with the survey
		  authoring language and tools. The system is capabile of conducting
		  extremely high volume online surveys and offers survey designers
		  flexible and powerful tools.
      </experience>
    </employment>

    <employment since="April, 1999" till="December, 2004">
      <company url="http://www.renderx.com/">RenderX</company>
      <position>Developer, CTO</position>
	  <experience>As a part of the startup from day one, designed one of the
		  first and still one of the best XSL formatting engines, <ulink
			  url="http://www.renderx.com/tools/xep.html">XEP</ulink>,
		  implemented core functionality, and led a team of engineers, writers,
		  and support staff. Authored several patents related to digital
		  typography and document processing.
	  </experience>
    </employment>

    <employment since="April, 1996" till="June, 1998">
      <company url="http://www.irex.org/">IREX</company>
      <position>Coordinator for US&#x2013;Armenia Internet Access and Training Program</position>
    </employment>

  </employments>

  <publications>
    <journalpubs>
      <publication>David Tolpin, Solomon Eyal Shimony. Semimyopic
       Measurement Selection for Optimization Under Uncertainty. IEEE
       Transactions on Systems, Man, and Cybernetics, Part B, Part B, 42(2):565–579, 2012</publication>
      <publication>David Tolpin, Solomon Eyal Shimony. Rational Value of Information Estimation for Measurement Selection. Intelligent Decision Technologies, 6(4):297--304, 2012.</publication>
	   <publication>David Tolpin, 2007. Probabilistic Networks for Knowledge Description. A Survey. Information Processes, Russian Academy of Sciences. 2007, Vol 1.</publication>
	</journalpubs>
	<conferencepubs>
        <publication>Eli Boyarski; Ariel Felner, Roni Stern, Guni Sharon; David Tolpin, Oded Betzalel, Solomon Eyal Shimony. ICBS: The Improved Conflict-based Search algorithm for Multi-Agent Pathfinding. IJCAI-2015.</publication>
		<publication>David Tolpin, Frank Wood. Maximum a Posteriori Estimation by Search in Probabilistic Programs. SOCS-15.</publication>
    <publication>David Tolpin, Oded Betzalel, Ariel Felner, Solomon Eyal Shimony. Rational Deployment of Multiple Heuristics in IDA*. ECAI-2014</publication>
    <publication>David Tolpin, Tal Beja, Solomon Eyal Shimony, Erez
    Karpas, Ariel Felner. Towards Rational Deployment of Multiple
    Heuristics in A*. IJCAI-2013</publication>

    <publication>Nicholas Hay, Stuart Russell, David Tolpin, Solomon Eyal Shimony. Selecting Computations: Theory and
    Applications. UAI-2012</publication>
    <publication>David Tolpin, Solomon Eyal Shimony. VOI-aware
    MCTS. ECAI-2012. pp. 929-930.</publication>
    <publication>David Tolpin, Solomon Eyal Shimony. MCTS Based on
    Simple Regret. AAAI-2012. pp. 570-576</publication>
    <publication>David Tolpin, Solomon Eyal Shimony. Rational Deployment of CSP Heuristics. IJCAI-2011. pp. 680-686</publication>
    <publication>David Tolpin, Solomon Eyal Shimony. Rational Value of Information Estimation for Measurement Selection. 25th Mini-EURO Conference: URPDM-2010. </publication>
	  </conferencepubs>
	  <patentpubs>
   <publication>David Tolpin, 2006. US Pat. 7024621: Methods and systems for rendering electronic data.</publication>
   <publication>David Tolpin, 2005. US Pat. 6971062: Methods for rendering footnotes.</publication>
   </patentpubs>
  </publications>
 
  <projects>
    <project since="November, 2014" till="current">
		<subject><ulink url="https://bitbucket.org/dtolpin/anglican">Probabilistic Programming System Anglican</ulink></subject>
		<para>
			<ulink url="https://bitbucket.org/dtolpin/anglican">Anglican</ulink>
			is a open source, just-in-time-compiled probabilistic
			programming language embedded in Clojure. Anglican is higher-order,
			Turing-complete, and supports accurate inference in models that
			make use of complex control flow, including stochastic recursion.
			It also includes primitives from Bayesian nonparametric statistics.
		</para>
		<para>Implemented Anglican, as a language embedded in <ulink
				url="http://clojure.org/">Clojure</ulink>. Community-maintained
			<ulink url="https://bitbucket.org/fwood/anglican-examples/">examples</ulink> of probabilistic programs written in Anglican cover a wide range of inference settings.
		</para>
	</project>

    <project since="October, 2003" till="March, 2004">
      <subject url="http://davidashen.net/rnv.html"><emphasis role="bold">RNV</emphasis> — Relax NG validator</subject>
      <para>
      RNV is an implementation of <ulink url="http://relaxng.org/">Relax NG</ulink> Compact Syntax validator in ANSI C.
      </para>
	  <para>The validator is widely used and is known to be conformant and the fastest implementation of Relax NG. 
     </para>
    </project>

    <project since="April, 1999" till="July, 2003">
      <subject url="http://www.renderx.com/tools/xep.html"><emphasis role="bold italic">XEP</emphasis> &#x2014; XSL Formatting Objects Rendering Engine</subject>
      <para>Designed and led a team of engineers to implement the first commercially available and still one of the best implementations
      of <ulink url="http://www.w3.org/TR/xsl">XSL Formatting Objects</ulink>. Wrote core modules of the formatting engine.
      </para>
    </project>

    <project since="1994" till="1996">
		<subject url="http://ftp.davidashen.net/RWWW/"><emphasis role="bold italic">rwww</emphasis> &#x2014; WWW Search Engine with Support for Russian Morphology</subject>
	  <para>Designed and implemented a non-dictionary stemming algorithm for
		  the Russian language (Rustem).  Wrote the stemming module in Scheme
		  and ANSI C.  Modified and improved <ulink
			  url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wide_area_information_server">freeWAIS</ulink>
		  to support 8-bit encodings and calls to external wordform
		  normalizers. Wrote a distributed WWW scanning robot.
      </para>
    </project>
  </projects>

  <miscellanea>
    <p>Languages: Hebrew, English, Yiddish, Armenian, Russian.</p>
  </miscellanea>


</resume>
